The Life Of Muhammadﷺ, Madinan Period Volume 2
By Imam Anwar Al-Awlaki,
اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ ۝ بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
Dear brothers and sisters,
السلام وعليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته
We're moving on, to the events of the 10th year of Hijrah(هجرة).
Rasool Allah ﷺ sent Muadh Ibn Jabal(معاذ ابن جبل) and Abu Musa Al-Ashha'ari(ابوموسى الأشعري)
to give Daw'ah(دعوة) to the people of Yemen.
And in Bukhari(بخاريْ) it says;
وَبَعَثَ كُلُّ وَاحِدٍ مِنْهُمَا عَلَى مَخْلَافْ
And he sent each one of them on a province.
So, everyone was an Ameer(امير) over a province and Yemen was two provinces at that time.
قالَ: واليَمَنُ مِخْلَافَانِ، ثُمَّ قالَ: يَسِّرَا ولَا تُعَسِّرَا، وبَشِّرَا ولَا تُنَفِّرَا، وَفِيْ رَوَايَةٍ وَتَطَاوَعَا وَلَا تَختَلِفَا
Rasool Allah ﷺ told them: Be lenient, not harsh, encourage rather than repress.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ them told; Cooperate and do not conflict.
In Da'wah(دعوة), leniency is needed, and not harshness.
There's a difference between Da'wah(دعوة) and Jihad(جهاد)
we find that, the Ayaat(آيات) and the Ahadith(احاديث), that talks about harshness with the Kuffar(كفار)
are in the context of fighting Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله),
and here you have Rasool Allah ﷺ, telling them to be lenient and not to be harsh,
and to encourage people and not to repress
because these are either people, who are new Muslim,
or they are people who are receptive to listening to the message of Islam.
فَانْطَلَقَ كُلُّ واحِدٍ منهما إلى عَمَلِهِ
And each one of them went to his province.
قَالَ: وَكَانَ كُلُّ واحِدٍ منهما إذَا سَارَ في أرْضِهِ كانَ قَرِيبًا مِن صَاحِبِهِ أحْدَثَ به عَهْدًا، فَسَلَّمَ عليه
They agreed that whenever one of them would be close to the other,
they should meet and renew the Salam(سلام) on each other.
Because both of them were traveling,
they were going from one village to another from one town to another.
So, whenever their paths run close to each other, they decided that they should meet and come together
and discuss their affairs and give Naseeha(نصيحه) to each other.
As we will see in this conversation.
فَسَارَ مُعَاذٌ في أرْضِهِ قَرِيبًا مِن صَاحِبِهِ أبِي مُوسَى
Muadh(معاذ) was close to the province of Abu Musa(ابوموسى).
فَجَاءَ يَسِيرُ علَى بَغْلَتِهِ حتَّى انْتَهَى إلَيْهِ
So, he came on his mount on his mule until, he reached to Abu Musa(ابو موسى).
فَاِذَا هو جَالِسٌ، وقَدِ اجْتَمع النَّاسُ إلَيْهِ
So, he saw him sitting and people were gathered around him.
وإذَا رَجُلٌ عِنْدَهُ قدْ جُمِعَتْ يَدَاهُ إلى عُنُقِهِ
And there was a man over there whose hands were tied to his neck.
فَقالَ له مُعَاذٌ: يا عَبْدَ اللَّهِ بنَ قَيْسٍ أيُّمَ هذا؟ قالَ: هذا رَجُلٌ كَفَرَ بَعْدَ إسْلَامِهِ
So, Muadh(معاذ) said: O Abdullah Bin Qais(عبد الله بن قيس), this is the name of Abu Musa(ابوموسى), who is this.?
He said: This is a man, who committed apostasy after being a Muslim.
In another narration, it says that this man was a Yahoodi(يهودي).
So, he was a Jew who became Muslim, and then went back to becoming a Jew again.
Muadh Ibn Jabal(معاذ ابن جبل) said;
لا أنْزِلُ حتَّى يُقْتَلَ
I am not coming down from my mount, until he is executed.
قالَ: إنَّما جِيءَ به لِذلكَ فَانْزِلْ
He said: That's why we brought him, so come down.
قالَ: ما أنْزِلُ حتَّى يُقْتَلَ
I am not coming down, until he is executed.
فأمَرَ به فَقُتِلَ
And he was executed then Muadh Ibn Jabal(معاذ ابن جبل) came down.
And he said;
يا عَبْدَ اللَّهِ، كيفَ تَقْرَأُ القُرْآنَ؟
O Abdullah(عبد الله), how do you recite Quran.?
قالَ: أتَفَوَّقُهُ تَفَوُّقًا
The meaning of what Abu Musa(ابوموسى) said.
Is that I read it continuously, piece after piece.
And this is from Taffuwuq(تفوق), the milking of a camel, it would be milked
and then left for a short while to rest and then milked again,
and then left for some time to rest and the milked again.
So, the milking process happens in intervals that are all throughout the day.
And that is how Abu Musa(ابوموسى) used to recite Qur'an
meaning he would read take a break, read take a break,
which means that he was reciting Quran continuously day and night.
And then he asked Muadh(معاذ);
فَكيفَ تَقْرَأُ أنْتَ يا مُعَاذُ؟
How do you recite O Muadh(معاذ).? Muadh(معاذ) said;
أنَامُ أوَّلَ اللَّيْلِ، فأقُومُ وقدْ قَضَيْتُ جُزْئِي مِنَ النَّوْمِ، فأقْرَأُ ما كَتَبَ اللَّهُ لِي، فأحْتَسِبُ نَوْمَتي كما أحْتَسِبُ قَوْمَتِي
He said: I sleep the first part of the night.
So, I wake up while I have taken my need of sleep,
and then I would recite whatever Allah destines for me to recite.
So, I would count my sleep to be an act, that I will be rewarded for,
just like I am rewarded for praying.
Muadh(معاذ) here is telling Abu Musa(ابوموسى) that even though you exhaust yourself in the recitation of Qur'an,
I take my need of rest.
And I count that rest as a Ibadah(عبادة).
Because the reason I'm doing it, is to be able to pray after that.
So, this shows you that even your habits,
your daily habits of sleeping, drinking, eating, washing, could be counted as something
that you have Ajr(أجر), a reward for, as long as you're doing them for the sake of Allah in order to give you ability to worship Him,
and to make you active when you are performing your rituals.
In another narration in Al-Bukhari(بخاريْ).
عَنْ اِبْنِ عَبَّاسْ رضي الله عنه قَالَ : قَالَ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لِمُعَاذ اِبن جبل، حِيْنَ بَعَثَه’ إِلَى الْيَمَنْ
إِنَّكَ ستأتي قَوْمًا أهلَ كتابٍ ، فإذا جئتَهم فادْعُهم إلى أنْ يشهدُوا أنْ لَا إِلَهَ إلَّا اللهُ ، وأنَّ محمَّدًا رسولَ اللهِ
Ibn Abbas(ابن عباس) says: When Rasool Allah ﷺ sent to Muadh(معاذ) to Yemen,
he told him, you are coming to a people who are a people of a book,
because the people of Yemen in Najraan(نجران), they were Christian, and many of the rest were Jews.
They were Arabs in ancestry, but they adopted the religion of Judaism.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ told him you're coming to a people, who are a people of a scripture,
so call them to testify that there is no one worthy of worship but Allah
and that Muhammad(محمد) is the Messenger of Allah.
فإِنْ هم أطاعوا لَكَ بذلِكَ ، فأخبرْهم أنَّ اللهَ قَدِ فرَضَ عليْهِمْ خمسَ صلَوَاتٍ في كُلِّ يومٍ وليلَةٍ ،
If they accept that, then tell them, that Allah has obligated on them five prayers every night and day.
فإِنْ هم أطاعوا لَكَ بذلِكَ ، فأخبرْهم أنَّ اللهَ قدْ فَرَضَ عليهم صَدَقَةً ، تُؤْخَذُ منْ أغنيائِهم ، فتردُّ على فُقَرَائِهِم
If they accept that, then tell them that Allah has obligated on them to pay Zakat(زكواة),
charity that is taken from the rich among them and given to the poor among them.
And this is evidence for the ones, who say that the
Zakat(زكواة) should be collected from a locality and spent in the same locality.
The evidence they use is this Hadith(حديث).
Now, the scholars say that that is better, however if the need is greater in another area,
then you can send the Zakat(زكواة) to another area or your Sadaqah(صدقه).
فإِنْ هم أطاعوا لَكَ بِذَلِكَ ، فإيَّاكَ وكرائِمَ أموالِهم
If they accept that then be aware of the best parts of their property.
Meaning, when you go to choose, for example, the animals that you will take for Zakat(زكواة) from the sheep or from the cattle,
do not choose the best, choose the average, not the worst, nor the best.
وَاتَّقِ دعوَةَ المظلومِ ، فإِنَّه ليسَ بينها وَبينَ اللهِ حجابٌ
And be aware from the prayers of the oppressed
because nothing stands between his prayers and Allah.
Rasool Allah ﷺ is telling Muadh(معاذ) to be careful do not oppress anyone.
Because if you do oppress anyone, and that person makes a Dua(دُعَا) against you,
that Dua(دُعَا) will reach Allahعَزّوجَلّ and nothing will stand between it and Allah.
So, we need to be carefulnot to oppress anyone,
because oppression is a great sin on the Day of Judgment.
You can also see from this Hadith(حديث) the step by step Da'wah(دعوة) that people should be taken step by step,
Shahadah(شهاده) first, then Salah(صلاة), then Zakat(زكواة).
In a narration by Imam Ahmad(امام احمد):
مُعَاذْ اَنَّه’ كَانَ يَقُوْلْ بَعَثَنِيْ رسولُ اللهِ صلَّى اللهُ عليه وسلَّم
إِلَى الْيَمَنِ فَقَالَ لَعَلَّكَ أَنْ تَمُرَّ بِقَبْرِيْ وَمَسْجِدِيْ
وَقَدْ بَعَثْتُكَ إِلَى قَوْمٍ رَقِيْقَةٍ قُلُوْبُهُمْ يُقَاتِلوْنَ عَلَى الْحَقِّ مَرَّتَيْنِ
فَقَاتِلْ بِمَنْ أَطَاعَكَ مِنْهُمْ مَنْ عَصَاكْ
ثُمَّ يَعودون إلى الإسلامِ
حتَّى تُبادِرَ الْمَرْأةُ زَوْجَها وَالْوَلَدُ وَالَدَه’ وَالْأخُ أَخَاهْ فَاَنْزِلْ بَيْنَ الْحيَّيْنِ اَلسَّكُوْنِ وَالسَّكَاسِكِ
Muadh Ibn Jabal(معاذ ابن جبل) said: Rasool Allah ﷺ sent me to Yemen and told me,
you may pass by my grave and my mosque.
This is an indication that Rasool Allah ﷺ would be meeting Muadh(معاذ) for the last time
and I'm sending you to a people, who have soft hearts and they will fight for the truth twice.
So, fight with those, who follow you, with the ones, who disobey you.
Rasool Allah ﷺ is telling Muadh Ibn Jabal(معاذ ابن جبل).
Make Daw'ah(دعوة) when people accept Islam, recruit them immediately
and use them to fight against those, who disbelieve.
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not tell Muadh Ibn Jabal(معاذ ابن جبل) to send them
to an Islamic University or to take them to special Tarbiyyah(تربية) sessions.
Not to say that knowledge is not important or Tarbiyyah(تربية) is not important.
But it shows you that if a person accepts Islam,
then the obligation of fighting for the religion is there
and this is what Rasool Allah ﷺ is telling Muadh Ibn Jabal(معاذ ابن جبل) to do,
to recruit them when they become Muslim to fight the ones, who did not become Muslim.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ told him that
when you fight with them against the ones, who disobey Islam will spread.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him that Islam will spread
and you would find that the woman would leave her husband
and the child would leave the parents and the brother would leave his brother
for the sake of Islam.
And in another narration by Imam Al-Ahmad(امام الاحمد).
اَنْ مُعَاذْ اِبْنِ جَبَل قَال: لَمَّا بَعَثَهُ رَسُولُ اللَّهِ صَلَّى اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ إِلَى الْيَمَنِ
خَرَجَ مَعَهُ يُوصِيهِ، وَمُعَاذٌ رَاكِبٌ وَرَسُولُ اللَّهِ صَلَّى اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ يَمْشِي تَحْتَ رَاحِلَتِهِ
When Rasool Allah ﷺ was sending Muadh Ibn Jabal(معاذ ابن جبل).
He was giving him Naseeha(نصيحة), advice.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ was walking, while Muadh(معاذ) was riding
and this is the humbleness and the simplicity of Rasool Ullah صلوات الله وسلام عليه
the head of state, the Prophet ﷺ, the greatest of mankind, he's walking
while Muadh Ibn Jabal(معاذ ابن جبل) is riding on his mount.
فَلَمَّا فَرَغَ قَالَ: " يَا مُعَاذُ، إِنَّكَ عَسَى أَلَّا تَلْقَانِي بَعْدَ عَامِي هَذَا
O Muadh(معاذ), you may not see me anymore after this year.
وَلَعَلَّكَ أَنْ تَمُرَّ بِمَسْجِدِي هَذَا وَقَبْرِي
And you may pass next to Mosque and my grave.
فَبَكَى مُعَاذٌ
Muadh(معاذ) cried.
ثُمَّ الْتَفَتَ بِوَجْهِهِ نَحْوَ الْمَدِينَةِ فَقَالَ
إِنَّ أَوْلَى النَّاسِ بِي الْمُتَّقُونَ مَنْ كَانُوا وَحَيْثُ كَانُوا
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ looked at Madina and said;
The people, who are closest to me are the people of Taqwa(تقوى) wherever they are, and whoever they are.
And this is a great Bushra(بشرة), rejoicing news from Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Rasool Ullah is saying that the closest people to him are the people, who have Taqwa(تقوى),
wherever they are, in any land they are, and whoever they are.
It doesn't matter what race or background they come from, as long as they are people of Taqwa(تقوى).
And other words of advice that Rasool Allah ﷺ gave Muadh Ibn Jabal(معاذ ابن جبل)
and this is also in Masnad Imam Ahmad(مسند ألإمام أحمد).
Rasool Allah ﷺ told Muadh Ibn Jabal(معاذ ابن جبل);
إِيَّاكَ وَالتَّنَعُّمَ فَإِنَّ عِبَادَ اللَّهِ لَيْسُوا بِالْمُتَنَعِّمِينَ
Beware of luxury, because the servants of Allah are not luxurious.
Muadh Ibn Jabal(معاذ ابن جبل) is sent to be, what.?
A governor.
So, it is a job that affords him luxury if he wants to.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ is warning him and telling him beware of luxury.
So, that is the advice Rasool Allah ﷺ was giving to a man, who afforded luxury.
How is it then, to the ones, who are not in positions of luxury
nevertheless, they forced themselves to live a life of luxury
and luxury in a way is a very dangerous thing
and Rasool Allah ﷺ is telling Muadh(معاذ), that the true servants of Allah are not luxurious.
And in another narration by Abdul Razzaq Sana'ani(عبدالرزاق صنعاني).
كَانَ مُعَاذُ بنُ جَبَلٍ شَابًّا جَمِيْلًا سَمْحًا مِنْ خَيْرِ شَبَابِ قَوْمِهْ
لَا يُسْئَلُ شَيْئًا إِلَّا أَعْطَاهْ حَتَّى كَانَ عَلَيْهِ دَيْنٌ أَغْلَقَ مَالَه
فَكَلَّمَ رسولَ الله ِفِيْ أَنْ يُكَلِّمَ غُرَمَاءَه’ فَفَعَلْ
فَلمْ يَضَعَوْا لَه’ شَيْئًا فَلَوْ تُرِكَ لَأحَدٍ بِكَلَامِ أَحَدٍ
لتُرِكَ لِمُعَاذٍ بِكَلَامِ رسولِ اللهِ صلَّى اللهُ عليه وسلَّمَ
Muadh Ibn Jabal(معاذ ابن جبل) was a handsome and generous young man,
one of the finest of his people,
Muadh(معاذ), by the way, was young, and was a very active student of knowledge.
And very close to Rasool Allah ﷺ
and Rasool Allah ﷺ gave him special attention
because Rasool Ullah used to love him and used to see, in him signs of a scholar.
So, in this Hadith(حديث) it says that Muadh Ibn Jabal(معاذ ابن جبل) was a handsome and generous young man,
one of the finest of his people, anything ever asked of him, he would give,
so that eventually he had a debt that foreclosed all of his money.
He told this Rasool Allah ﷺ and asked him to speak to his creditors and this Rasool Allah ﷺ did.
However, the creditors did not excuse Muadh(معاذ) of anything,
even though Rasool Allah ﷺ interceded on his behalf.
So, than his wealth was all split up, he lost, he became bankrupt.
So, all of his wealth was split up among the creditors.
فَقَامَ مُعَاذٌ وَلَا مَالَ لَه
By the time Muadh(معاذ) left, he had nothing.
قَالَ: فَلَمَّا حَجَّ رسولُ اللهِ بَعَثَ مُعَاذًا إِلَى الْيَمَنِ قَالَ فَكَانَ أَوَّلً مَنْ تَجَرَ فِيْ هَذَا الْمَال مُعاذٌ
When Rasool Allah ﷺ made Hajj(حج), he sent Muadh(معاذ) to Yemen.
And he allowed him to invest the money that was under his authority,
the money of the Treasury, he was allowed to invest it and he was the first one to do so.
قَالَ: فَقَدِمَ عَلى أبي بكرٍ الصديقِ مِنَّ الْيَمَنِ وَقَدْ تُوُفِّيَ رسولُ اللهِ صلَّى اللهُ عليه وسلَّمَ
فَجَاءَ عمرُ فقال: هَلْ لَّكَ أَنْ تُعْطِيَنِيْ فَتَدْفَعَ
هذا المال إِلَى أَبِي بكرٍ
فَإِنْ أَعْطَاكَه’ فَاقْبَلْه قال فقال : معاذٌ لَن أَدْفَعْه’ إِلَيْه وَإنَّمَا بَعَثَنِي رسولُ اللهِ لِيُجْبِرَنِيْ
By the time Muadh Ibn Jabal(معاذ ابن جبل) came back, Rasool Allah ﷺ has already passed away
and it was the time of the Khilafah(خِلَافَه) of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
and his investment of the money was successful.
And Umar(عمر) told Muadh(معاذ), give this money back to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), if he gives you anything of it then fine.
Otherwise, you should give it up.
Muadh(معاذ) said: I'm not gonna give it up.
Because Rasool Allah ﷺ sent me with the intention of having me, gain some money again,
because of the story that we just talked about, he lost all of his money.
So, Umar(عمر) went to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and told him that
أَرْسِلْ إِلَى هَذَا الرَّجُلِ فَخُذْ مِنْه’ وَدَعْ لَهْ
Sent to this man and take some of his wealth and leave him some.
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said:
مَا كُنْتُ لِأفْعَلَ إِنَّمَا بَعَثَه’ رسولُ اللهِ صلى الله عليه وسلم لِيُجْبِرَه
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) refused and said that Rasool Allah ﷺ has sent him(this money)
in order that he wants him to benefit himself or to improve himself financially after he went bankrupt.
In the morning Muadh Ibn Jabal(معاذ ابن جبل) went to Umar(عمر) and said;
مَا أَرَنِيْ إِلَّا فَاعِلٌ اَلَّذِيْ قُلْتُ
I think that I'm going to do what you told me.
إِنِّيْ رَأَيْتَنِيْ الْبَارِحَةَ فِيْ النَّوْمْ
I saw myself in my dream.
أُجَرُّ إِلَى النَّارِ
I was being dragged to Hellfire and you were the one, who was holding me back.
So, he went to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and gave him everything
and then Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه gave it to him back and said it is Halal(حلال) for you.
So now, it was given to him with the approval of the Khalifah(خليفه).
Rasool Allah صلوات الله وسلام عليه also sent Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) to Yemen and he sent Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب),
In Al-Bayhaqi(البيهقي) it says:
عَنِ الْبَرَآءْ اَنَّ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بَعَثَ خَالد ابن وليد اِلَى اليمن يَدْعُوْهُمْ اِلَى الْاِسْلَامْ
Rasool Allah ﷺ has sent Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) to Yemen to call them to Islam.
He stayed there for six months and people were not very receptive to his Da'wah(دعوة).
Rasool Allah ﷺ called him back and sent Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) in his place.
And he told Ali(علي) to allow whoever wants to go back with Khalid(خالد) to go back
and whoever wants to stay behind with Ali(علي), it's up to them.
And then Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب)
ثُمَّ تَقَدِّمَ بِنَا فَصَلَّى بِنَا عَلِيْ
And this was in front of the tribe of Hamdaan(همدان),
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) had of the Muslims line up, and then he prayed Jama'ah(جماعة).
And then he had them also line up and he stood in front of them.
And he opened up the letter from Rasool Allah ﷺ and he read it to them.
فَاَسْلَمَتْ هَمْدَانْ جَمِيْعَا
All of Hamdan(همدان) the entire tribe became Muslim.
فَكَتَبَ عَلِي اِلَى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بِاِسْلَامِهِمْ
Ali(علي) wrote back to Rasool Allah ﷺ, giving him the good news.
فَلَمَّا قَرَأْ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم الكِتَابْ خَرَّ سَاجِدَاً
ثُمَّ رَفَعَ رَأْسَه’ فَقَالَ: اَلسَّلَامُ عَلَى هَمْدَانْ، اَلسَّلَامُ عَلَى هَمْدَانْ
When Rasool Allah ﷺ received a letter from Ali(علي), telling him the good news.
Rasool Ullah صلوات الله وسلام عليه made Sujood(سجود) and then said;
May peace be on Hamdan(همدان). May peace be on Hamdan(همدان).
Ali(علي) also says;
بَعثَنِيْ رَسُوْلُ اللَّهِ صلَّى اللَّهُ عليهِ وسلَّمَ إِلَى الْيَمَنِ قال ، فقُلتُ: يا رسولَ اللَّهِ
تَبَعَثْنِيْ اِلَى قَوْمٍ اَسَّنَّ مِنِّيْ وَاَنَا حَدَثٌ لَا اُبْصِرُالْقَضَاءْ
O Messenger of Allah, You're sending me to a people who are older than me,
because Ali(علي) was very young and he was appointed as Judge over them
and I'm young in age and I don't have experience in being a judge.
قَالَ فَوَضَعَ يَدَهُ عَلى صَدري وقالَ : اللّهُمَّ ثَبِّتْ لِسانَهُ وَهْدِ قَلبَهُ
يَا عَلِيُّ ، إِذَا جَلَسَ إِلَيْكَ الْخَصْمَانِ فَلا تَقْضِ بَيْنَهُمَا حَتَّى تَسْمَعَ مِنَ الْآخَرِ كَمَا سَمِعْتَ مِنَ الْأَوَّلِ
فَإِنَّكَ إِذَا فَعَلْتَ ذَلِكَ تَبَيَّنَ لَكْ
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ put his hand on the chest of Ali(علي) and said;
O Allah, make his tongue firm and guide his heart.
O Ali(علي), When the two people who are disputing come and sit under you.
Do not judge between them, until you hear from them both.
If you do that, then it will be easy for you to judge.
قَالَ: مَاخْتَلَفَ عَلَيَّ قَضَاءٌ بَعْدْ
I was never confused in making a judgment after that.
And Ali(علي) is very famous of being a judge.
And he was a judge in the time of Umar(عمر) and he was a judge in the time of Uthman(عثمان).
They used to trust his judgment very much and they would appoint him to judge over the delicate cases
that would be presented to the Islamic government.
Rasool Ullah صلوات الله وسلام عليه made Hajj(حج) in the 10th year of Hijrah(هجرة).
And this is called the farewell Hajj(حج)
because it is the Hajj(حج) where Rasool Allah ﷺ delivered to the Ummah(امة) his final words,
and it was a time when all of the Muslims congregated and had a chance to hear and see
from Rasool Ullah صلوات الله وسلام عليه for the last time
and it is also called Hajjatel Islam(حجة الاسلام),
the Hajj(حج) of Islam because it is the only Hajj(حج) Rasool Allah ﷺ made from Madina.
Rasool Allah ﷺ did make Hajj(حج) while he was in Makkah
before Prophethood and after Prophethood
but this was the only Hajj(حج), he did in Madina and it is 10 years after his Hijrah(هجرة).
Rasool Allahصلوات الله وسلام عليه made Hajj(حج) riding on his camel
and he had very humble riding equipment, the saddle that is used for the camel
and Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
حِجَّةً لَا رِيَاءَ فِيهَا وَلا سُمْعَةَ
A Hajj(حج) with no show, Rasool Allah ﷺ made his Hajj(حج) simple.
And that is how Hajj(حج) should be, simple clothes
and a Muslim should use Hajj(حج) as a chance to get out of the accustomed ease
that he has, otherwise in his life.
It is a time to experience a bit of hardship.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ made his Hajj(حج) very simple.
In the time after Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away and the condition of the Muslims was improving very much financially.
So, now, people are coming to Hajj(حج) with more fancy things.
So, Ibn Umar(ابن عمر) was with his companions.
And then a group of Hujjaj(حجاج) coming from Yemen,
passed in front of Ibn Umar(ابن عمر), so he told the people, who were with him.
مَنْ اَحَبَّ اَن يَّنْظُرَ اِلَى اَشْبَهِ رِفقَةٍ وَرَدَت الْعَامْ بِرَسول لله صلى الله عليه وسلم
وَاَصْحَابَه’ اِذْ قَدِمُوْا فِيْ حَجَّةِ الْوِدَاعْ فَلْيَنْظُرْ اِلَى هَذِهِ الرَّفقَهْ
In Musnad Imam Ahmad(مسند ألإمام أحمد): When these men from Yemen passed in front of Ibn Umar(إبن عُمر),
they had a very easy or simple riding saddles on their camels and they were wearing very simple Ihraams(احرام) and clothes.
So, Ibn Umar(ابن عمر) said;
Whoever wants to see the most similar travelers this year, to Rasool Allah ﷺ and his companions
when they made Hajj(حج), then look at these.
So, if you go to Makkah today, and you go to Madina today, in the time of Hajj(حج),
you would see extravagance, you would see fancy Hajj(حج), you would see the VIP Hajj(حج).
And Hajj(حج) which is supposed to be equal for everyone
has become a place where you can clearly see the difference between the rich and poor
in their accommodation and in their transportation and in another aspects also,
and that is not how it was in the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ was in Arafah(عرفه).
Allahعَزّوجَلّ revealed to Muhammad صلوات الله وسلام عليه.
الْيَوْمَ أَكْمَلْتُ لَكُمْ دِينَكُمْ وَأَتْمَمْتُ عَلَيْكُمْ نِعْمَتِي وَرَضِيتُ لَكُمُ الْإِسْلَامَ دِينًا
Allahعَزّوجَلّ revealed to Muhammadﷺ that today your religion is complete,
and My blessings on you are completed.
And it is pleasing for Allah to have your religion as Islam.
A Jew came to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) and said: O, Ameer Ul Momineen(امير المؤمنين),
this is when Umar(عمر) was a Khalifah(خليفه) he told him;
If this verse was revealed to us, we would have taken that day as a day of celebration, as a day of Eid(عيد).
Because it's such a great Ayah(آية) when you think about,
you know that your religion now is complete.
Every Muslim now knows that his religion that he is following is a complete religion.
Everything is in there.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said;
I know when that Ayah(آية) was revealed, it was revealed on Arafah(عرفه) and it was on Friday.
Umm-Ul-Hussain(ام الحصين) and this is a in Muslim(مسلم).
تَقُوْل: حَجَجْتُ مَعَ رَسولِ اللهِ صَلَّى اللَّهُ عليه وسلَّمَ حَجَّةَ الوَدَاعِ
فَرَأَيْتُهُ حِينَ رَمَى جَمْرَةَ العَقَبَةِ، وَانْصَرَفَ وَهو علَى رَاحِلَتِهِ وَمعهُ بلَالٌ وَأُسَامَةُ
أَحَدُهُما يَقُودُ به رَاحِلَتَهُ، وَالآخَرُ رَافِعٌ ثَوْبَهُ علَى رَأْسِ رَسولِ اللهِ صَلَّى اللَّهُ عليه وسلَّمَ مِنَ الشَّمْسِ
قالَتْ: فَقالَ رَسولُ اللهِ صَلَّى اللَّهُ عليه وسلَّمَ قَوْلًا كَثِيرًا،
ثُمَّ سَمِعْتُهُ يقولُ: إنْ أُمِّرَ علَيْكُم عَبْدٌ مُجَدَّعٌ، حَسِبْتُهَا قالَتْ، أَسْوَدُ
يَقُودُكُمْ بكِتَابِ اللهِ تَعَالَى، فَاسْمَعُوا لَه’ وَأَطِيعُوا
Umm Hussain(ام الحصين) said: I made Hajj(حج) with Rasool Ullah صلوات الله وسلام عليه
and then I saw him, when he threw the stones in Jumrat Ul Aqabah(جمرت العقبه).
And then he came back riding on his camel and with him was Bilal(بلال) and Osama(اسامه).
One of them was leading the camel
and the other one was raising his clothes over the head of Rasool Allah ﷺ to provide him with shade from the sun.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ said many things and I remember from the things that he said,
if a slave with chopped off limbs is appointed as a leader over you,
and he is leading you with the book of Allah, listen to him and obey.
An-Nawwawi(النووي) says;
وَمِنْ هَذِه الصِفَّاتْ مَجْمُوْعَة فِيْهِ فَهُوَ فِيْ نِهَايَتِ الْخِصَّهْ
He said: Whoever has all of these qualities in him.
He is at the lowest level, I mean he's a slave and his limbs are cut.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ is telling us that even if such a person is appointed over you,
as long as he is ruling with the book of Allah you should listen and obey.
فَاَمَرَ صلى الله عليه وسلم بِطَاعَة وَلِيِّ الْاَمْر
And Rasool Allah ﷺ ordered to follow the ones, who are appointed over us
as long as they are doing so, with the book of Allah.
قَالَ الْعُلَمَاءْ مَعْنَاهُمَا دَامٌ مُّتَّمَسِّكِيْنَ بِالْاِسْلَامِ وَالدُعَاءِ اِلَى كِتَابِ الله تعالى عَلَى اِيَّ حَالٍ كَانُوْا فِيْ اَنْفُسِهِمْ وَاَدْيَانِهِمْ وَاَخْلَاقِهِمْ
He said: The meaning of this is.
As long as they are following Islam and they are inviting people to the book of Allah,
regardless of what they are applying in their own selves.
And regardless of how their character is.
So, the meaning of this is,
if the laws are according to the book of Allah,
and if they are implementing the rule of Allah and inviting others to it,
it doesn't matter how their personal character is or what they are doing in their own privacy.
That is not something that should concern us as long as they are ruling according to the book of Allah.
And then he says;
وَلَا يُشَقَّ عَلَيْهِمُ الْعَصَى
And people should not revolt against such rulers.
بَلْ اِذَا ظَهَرَتْ مِنْهُمْ الْمُنْكَرَاتْ وُعِظُوا وَذكِرُوْا
But if they do something that is wrong, they should be given Naseeha(نصيحه).
فَاِنْ قِيْلَ كَيْفَ يُؤمَرْ بِسَّمْعَ وَالطَّاعَةْ لِلْعَبْد مَعَ نَشَرْتَ الْخَلِيْفَهْ اَنْ يَكُوْنُوْ قُرَيْشِيْ؟
The question arises,
how can you follow a slave when we know that the Khalifah(خليفه) should be from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)?
The answer is two sided, one!
اَنَّ الْمُرَادْ بَعْضَ الْوُلَآءْ اَلَّذِيْنَ يُوَلِّيْهُمُ الْخَلِيْفَهْ وَنُوَابَ
This is what meant here is that the Khalifah(خليفه) is the one, who appointed this person.
So, it's not talking about the Khalifah(خليفه).
لَااَنْ يَكُنْ خَلِيْفَه عَبْدًا وَثَانِيْ اَنَّ الْمُرَادَ لَوْقَهَرَ عَبْدٌ
مُسْلِمٌ وَاسْتَوْلی بِالْقَهَرْ نَفَذَتْ اَحْكَامُه’ وَوَجَبَتْ طَاعَتُه’وَلَمْ يَجُزْ شَقَّ الْعَصَا الِيه وَلله اَعْلَمْ
He said: If a slave takes over a government and that's it,
he has set himself he lodged himself in position of leadership, then his rule applies
and it is mandatory to follow him as long as he is ruling according to the book of Allah.
Rasool Allah ﷺ delivered a speech which is known as Khutbah Tul Widaah(خطبة الوداع),
the speech of farewell.
And there are various narrations of this some in Bukhari(بخاريْ), some in Muslim(ألمسلم),
some in the books of Seerah(سيرة), some in the other books of Sunnan(سنن).
And I'll go through the one narrated by Al-Imam Ahmad(ألإمام أحمد).
And we'll read the translation of it In Sha Allah(ان شاءالله)
and these are final words of advice from Rasool Ullah صلوات الله وسلام عليه.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
يَا أَيُّهَا النَّاسُ أَتَدْرُونَ فِي أَيِّ شَهْرٍ أَنْتُمْ وَفِي أَيِّ يَوْمٍ أَنْتُمْ وَفِي أَيِّ بَلَدٍ أَنْتُمْ
قَالُوا: فِي يَوْمٍ حَرَامٍ وَشَهْرٍ حَرَامٍ وَبَلَدٍ حَرَامٍ
قَالَ: فَإِنَّ دِمَاءَكُمْ وَأَمْوَالَكُمْ وَأَعْرَاضَكُمْ عَلَيْكُمْ حَرَامٌ
كَحُرْمَةِ يَوْمِكُمْ هَذَا فِي شَهْرِكُمْ هَذَا فِي بَلَدِكُمْ هَذَا إِلَى يَوْمِ تَلْقَوْنَهُ
ثُمَّ قَالَ: اِسْمَعُوا مِنِّي تَعِيشُوا أَلَا لَا تَظْلِمُوا أَلَا لَا تَظْلِمُوا أَلَا لَا تَظْلِمُوا
إِنَّهُ لَا يَحِلُّ مَالُ امْرِئٍ مُسلم إِلَّا بِطِيبِ نَفْسٍ مِنْهُ
أَلَا وَإِنَّ كُلَّ دَمٍ وَمَالٍ وَمَأْثَرَةٍ كَانَتْ فِي الْجَاهِلِيَّةِ تَحْتَ قَدَمِيَّ هَذِهِ إِلَى يَوْمِ الْقِيَامَةِ
وَإِنَّ أَوَّلَ دَمٍ يُوضَعُ دَمُ رَبِيعَةَ بْنِ الْحَارِثِ بْنِ عَبْدِ الْمُطَّلِبِ
كَانَ مُسْتَرْضِعًا فِي بَنِي سَعْدٍ لَيْثٍ فَقَتَلَتْهُ هُذَيْلٌ
أَلَا وَإِنَّ كُلَّ رِبًا كَانَ فِي الْجَاهِلِيَّةِ مَوْضُوعٌ وَإِنَّ اللَّهَ عَزَّ وَجَلَّ قَضَى أَنَّ أَوَّلَ رِبًا يُوضَعُ رِبَا الْعَبَّاسِ بْنِ عَبْدِ الْمُطَّلِبِ
لَكُمْ رُءُوسُ أَمْوَالِكُمْ لَا تَظْلِمُونَ وَلَا تُظْلَمُونَ
أَلَا وَإِنَّ الزَّمَانَ قَدْ اسْتَدَارَ كَهَيْئَتِهِ يَوْمَ خَلَقَ اللَّهُ السَّمَوَاتِ وَالْأَرْضَ
ثُمَّ قَرَأَ ‏إِنَّ عِدَّةَ الشُّهُورِ عِنْدَ اللَّهِ اثْنَا عَشَرَ شَهْرًا فِي كِتَابِ اللَّهِ يَوْمَ خَلَقَ السَّمَوَاتِ وَالْأَرْضَ مِنْهَا أَرْبَعَةٌ حُرُمٌ ‏
‏ذَلِكَ الدِّينُ الْقَيِّمُ فَلَا تَظْلِمُوا فِيهِنَّ أَنْفُسَكُمْ‏‏‏
أَلَا لَا تَرْجِعُوا بَعْدِي كُفَّارًا يَضْرِبُ بَعْضُكُمْ رِقَابَ بَعْضٍ
أَلَا إِنَّ الشَّيْطَانَ قَدْ يِئسَ أَنْ يَعْبُدَهُ الْمُصَلُّونَ وَلَكِنَّهُ فِي التَّحْرِيشِ بَيْنَكُمْ
فَاتَّقُوا اللَّهَ عَزَّ وَجَلَّ فِي النِّسَاءِ فَإِنَّهُنَّ عِنْدَكُمْ عَوَانٌ
لَا يَمْلِكْنَ لِأَنْفُسِهِنَّ شَيْئًا وَإِنَّ لَهُنَّ عَلَيْكُمْ حَقًا وَلَكُمْ عَلَيْهِنَّ حَقًّ أَنْ لَا يُوطِئْنَ فُرُشَكُمْ أَحَدًا غَيْرَكُمْ
وَلَا يَأْذَنَّ فِي بُيُوتِكُمْ لِأَحَدٍ تَكْرَهُونَهُ
فَإِنْ خِفْتُمْ نُشُوزَهُنَّ فَعِظُوهُنَّ وَاهْجُرُوهُنَّ فِي الْمَضَاجِعِ وَاضْرِبُوهُنَّ ضَرْبًا غَيْرَ مُبَرِّحٍ
وَلَهُنَّ رِزْقُهُنَّ وَكِسْوَتُهُنَّ بِالْمَعْرُوفِ، وَإِنَّمَا أَخَذْتُمُوهُنَّ بِأَمَانَةِ اللَّهِ
وَاسْتَحْلَلْتُمْ فُرُوجَهُنَّ بِكَلِمَةِ اللَّهِ عَزَّ وَجَلَّ ألاوَمَنْ كَانَتْ عِنْدَهُ أَمَانَةٌ فَلْيُؤَدِّهَا إِلَى مَنْ ائْتَمَنَهُ عَلَيْهَا
وَبَسَطَ يَدَيْهِ فَقَالَ أَلَا هَلْ بَلَّغْتُ أَلَا هَلْ بَلَّغْتُ، أَلَا هَلْ بَلَّغْتُ
ثُمَّ قَالَ لِيُبَلِّغْ الشَّاهِدُ الْغَائِبَ فَإِنَّهُ رُبَّ مُبَلَّغٍ أَسْعَدُ مِنْ سَامِعٍ
Rasool Allah ﷺ says, O people,
Do you know on which day, and which month, and in which land you are?
They replied: On a sacred day, of a sacred month, in a sacred land.
Rasool Allah said: Your blood, your possessions and your honor are sacred for you.
As Is this your day, in this your month, in this your land, on until you meet Him?
And then he said: Listen to me, you would live.
Do not do wrong! Do not do wrong! Do not do wrong.!
The property of a Muslim is not permitted to you, except by his wish.
All blood, money and deeds done in the Jahilliyah(جاهلية) are crushed beneath these feet of mine until Judgment Day.
The first blood that abolished is that of a Ibn Rabia Bin Haris Bin Abdul Muttalib(ابن ربيعه بن حارث بن عبد المطلب).
He was fostered among Bannu Saad(بنو سعد) and Hudail(هديل) killed him,
all the usury charges of the Jahilliyah(جاهلية) are abolished.
Allah has decreed that the first usury charges to be abolished are those of Al-Abbas Bin Abdul Muttalib(العباس بن عبد المطلب),
your capital is your own,
no wrong should be done against you and you should not wrong anyone.
So, you can see that Rasool Allah ﷺ is putting all of Jahilliyah(جاهلية) behind.
This is a new era and new laws and the old era is gone
and Rasool Allah ﷺ is applying these rules on himself first and his family.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ is saying; The first thing of the killing of Jahilliyah(جاهلية) is gone
and we are going to give up the case of Ibn Rabia Bin Haris Bin Abdul Muttalib(ابن ربيعه بن حارث بن عبد المطلب),
who is the son of the cousin of Rasool Ullah صلوات الله وسلام عليه.
And this was a case that happened in the time of Jahilliyah(جاهلية).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ because these draw to wars and tribes fighting each other.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ is saying that that blood we are forgiving the ones, who killed him for it.
To put an end to the feudal system of Arabia,
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ is banning usury and Rasool Allah ﷺ is saying the first Ribaa(رباء)
that I'm putting under my feet is the Ribaa(رباء), of Al-Abbas(ألعباس).
So, Al-Abbas(ألعباس) was lending people and he was charging them interest
and Rasool Allah ﷺ was saying that all what you can get back is your capital.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ said time has revolved,
as was its fashion by the day, Allah created the heavens and the earth,
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ recited the Ayah(آية), the number of the months
with Allah is 12 months and in Allah's ordinance, since the day he created the heavens and the earth,
of these four are sacred.
That is the correct reckoning.
Therefore, do not harm yourselves regarding them.
This is in Surah At-Taubah(سورة التوبة), verse 36.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ says: Do not revert after me into unbelievers striking the necks of one another.
Satan has despaired that those, who pray will worship Him,
however, he is present in the dissension between yourselves.
And this is why we find a lot of dissension between the Muslims.
Shaytan(شيطان) does not care, does not bother about causing dissension among the Kuffar(كفار)
because there are the Kuffar(كفار) and going to Hellfire anyway.
But he is concerned about the Muslims since he cannot make them Kuffar(كفار),
he is making them fight among themselves, he is always instigating
this Waswassah(وسوسه) in the hearts of Muslims and causing Fitnah(فتنه) among them.
Fear Allah, in your relationship with women.
They are captives with you.
Rasool Allah ﷺ here in the last days of his life is giving us a Naseeha(نصيحه), to care for our women,
they are captives with you, they own nothing for themselves.
They have rights over you and you have rights over them,
that they should not allow anyone other than yourselves to set foot in your furnishings.
And they should not give permission to anyone, who dislike to enter your homes.
If you fear those of them who are fractious, then admonish them
and leave them in the beds and strike them but not viciously.
They have rights to their provisions and their clothing in kindness.
It was only by Allah's covenant that you took them and it is by Allah's word
that you are permitted access to them
and whoever has a covenant should discharge it, to whomever entrusted it to him.
These are the words of Rasool Allah ﷺ in Al-Hajj(الحج) Khutbah(خطبه) that was delivered to thousands of Muslims
and we find in them Tauheed(توحيد), we find in them advice for Fiqh(فقه)
and we also find Rasool Allah ﷺ giving us Naseeha(نصيحه) to care and have concern for the Muslimaat(مسلمات).
وَصَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْراً
وَالسلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته